eh London Institute of neurology and
will be the
just after his talk
thank you very much that's a great
pleasure to be here as some of you will
know I'm slightly outside my comfort
zone we've had a very very long way
outside my comfort zone
I found the talks this morning
intriguing a lot of the rhetoric I don't
understand but there's also a lot of
curious similarities between many issues
that we deal with in theoretical
neurobiology let me move this hour his
fame that I found a lot of the the
rhetoric and the ideas slightly mystical
that I've been hearing about but there
was also a lot of formal similarities
between some of the issues the wheels we
deal with in theoretical neurobiology
and in particular asking questions about
how the brain actively infers and codes
and exchanges with its environment so I
think from your perspective you can
regard me as the light entertainment of
this workshop so what I'm going to do is
try to an overview for you the basic
principles that we bring to bear when
trying to understand action and
deception in the brain with a particular
emphasis on not geometry per se but only
the information geometry and the
variation and the variational
underpinnings of them and hopefully
touched on some of the issues that we've
been hearing about in the previous talk
so let me overview for you
what we're going to talk about I'm gonna
start off in a very abstract way just
asking some basic questions about the
nature of self-organizing systems and in
particular biological systems and I'm
going to place center stage the boundary
between me or an agent and the outside
world with which the agent exchanges and
in particular I'm gonna focus on the
statistical notion of a Markov blanket
that separates me
the rest of the world and ask what it
means to have a Markov blanket and yet
still preserve a an ergodic exchange
with the world that means that I can
preserve certain states or I pursue
certain trajectories in terms of mice of
internal and external states I'm going
to illustrate the nature of those
principles by simulating a little
primordial soup and generating a little
agent within that primordial soup and
performing some experiments upon it
having established the basic idea and
some of the principles I'm going to tell
exactly the same story but from the
point of view of a neuroscientist and
looking at the form of the variational
principles as they might be expressed in
the brain and in particular looking at
the notion of predictive coding and its
implementation in canonical micro
circuits in the brain and then I'm going
to illustrate those variational
principles with a few toys simulations
and these are going to be very very toy
from your perspective they're very
simple but they are at least illustrate
the basic idea I'm going to focus on
action and it's observation and then if
we have time conclude with a simulation
of eye movements and the sampling of
visual information from the world so I'm
going to start again I apologize for
being very abstract but I think it's
quite important from my perspective at
least just to motivate the underlying if
I was going to be a gradient descent it
could be a Gauss Newton or a gradient
descent the underlying dynamic that
we're going to be using so I'm going to
start here
well the question posed by severity and
yet how can the events in space and time
which take place within the spatial
boundary of a living organism be
accounted for by physics and chemistry
now I'm not going to answer that
question without what I want to
highlight is a notion of a spatial
boundary I've got the deeper question
underlying this question how do systems
induce and maintain the separation of
the spatial boundary between themselves
and the rest
the universe and he would be the first
person to acknowledge that that boundary
itself is a statistical object and in
statistics that would call that would
come that would be basically a Markov
blanket so a Markov bank is going to be
a statistical boundary between some
internal states of the system which I'll
denote by blue here and external states
in see on here that provides an
installation of a statistical sort
between say my States and States for the
rest of the world
so I'm how many people here know what a
Markov blanket is good could you explain
to your friends what a Markov blanket is
yes basics ain't an absolutely correct
okay but let me briefly unpack that for
if that I'm joking I think most of you
here do know after Markov blanket is so
can you put your hand up if you know
what a Markov processes yeah so you all
know essentially what a Markov blanket
is so in a with a Markov process in time
the Markov blanket is just the
proceeding state so it's just as it's
just the states you would need to know
that contain all the information about
the rest of possible knowledge in all
the remaining states in order to predict
the current the state of reference or
the internal states here so I if I
wanted to predict this state given the
causal influences of all other states it
will be sufficient just to know the
Markov blanket and I don't need to know
all the remaining so these are now
conditionally independent of these or
vice-versa conditioned upon the Markov
values and the Markov blanket comprises
the parents the children and the parents
of the children of the state now the
moral point of view there's an
interesting bipartition
on that Markov blanket
that is induced just by considering
states that are and states that are not
influenced by the internal states so for
any system that can be written down in
this form in terms of statistical
dependences there will exist a Markov
blanket and that Markov blanket can
always be split into two sets which I'm
going to call active states and in
sensory today to know I'm going to
motivate those labels just by asking you
to consider that causal structure in
relation to things that we know and love
by our biotic or biological things from
simple single cells through to say
brains here so the internal States will
correspond to all the internal states of
the cell the active States could be the
actin filaments that support the surface
states of the sensory states and provide
the cell with motility while the sensory
states are caused by external states
here that in turn influence internal
states that cause change in active
States that gain coupled back up to the
environment and exactly the same
slightly sparse causal structure can be
found in the brain we have the internal
states of the brain all the synaptic
activities connection strengths and the
like that influence and cause changes in
our actuators or a texture organs that
influence or changed external states
that are registered by sensory states
that in turn change the internal states
so I'm just saying that for any system
and any organism or agent or robot
embedded in a larger system we can
always apply this partition provided
certain conditioning dependencies exist
and I thought they have to exist in
order to produce a distinction between
me and the rest of the world through my
Markov blanket and now gonna ask you
should forget about that because what
we're going to do is I'll just look at
the generic behavior of all interesting
systems and then come back and put the
back of Duncan back into the equation
and see what the implications are for
the behavior of the sensitive states the
internal states and the action states
so just to motivate them so this is
going to be one of a couple of slides
with lots of equations or some equations
on and this is the basic slide that
motivates the variational approach
information geometric approach to the
dynamics of these systems and what I'm
doing here as if in an abstract weight
is taking any random dynamical system
where I'm lumping together states of the
world and control straight into X and
having random fluctuations and I'm
presupposing that we're only going to be
talking about systems that have
measurable characteristics that persist
over time so by definition they are at
Golic in a week at cents and that
implies the existence of a random
dynamical attractor so we have two
states here and they trace out a
manifold or attracting set here as time
evolves with multiple trajectories and
we can interpret that ensemble of
trajectories or attracting set in terms
of an ergodic probability the
probability theis sampled the system at
any point in time the probability of I
would find it in that state will be
denoted by the density here of these
trajectories so this could be say the
states of a system whilst walking for
example so if this attracting set exists
if the system exists then it is equipped
with all it has this probabilistic
description that can be described by the
proper Planck equation is is this a
familiar object to many people here yeah
okay also known as a master equation
Congre forward equation lots of
different names for those people who
don't know it's relatively simple I just
explain what it does in a second but
from our perspective it's form is not
terribly important what is important is
it is its solution because if this
attracting set exists then the rate of
change of this probability is zero which
means I can rearrange the solution to
express the flow of states as a function
of the gradients of the log probably
distribution so this is the solution
that I'm going to filter it is this one
solution here that I'm going to use as a
variational principle to understand all
internal state changes and all action
open systems that exist just
heuristically for those people who are
not familiar with the fokker-planck
formalism it's very simple all it's
saying here is that if you imagine just
dropping it's a drop of ink into the
ocean then these random fluctuations
they will disappear the concentration of
being throughout the ocean so in that
instance it wouldn't happen attracting
said he wouldn't have behaviors and we
can measure and admire or put on YouTube
so it must be the case then that there
is some deterministic flow that is
countering the dispersive forces so it's
acting in opposition to the dispersion
which degrades areas of high
concentration high probability the
distribution or density in other words
it's actually flowing towards regions of
high concentration and when those two
dispersive and deterministic flow
components are in balance then the
system becomes attains non equilibrium
steady state and is we clear Datuk and
that's all that we're describing here
this equation here is just an expression
of the Helmholtz decomposition is is
this expressing this flow in terms of a
hill climbing or gradient ascent on the
log probability and a solenoidal or
divergence free component that actually
breaks the detailed balance of these of
a system in general and we're going to
use both terms later on in a way which I
think many people will be more familiar
with and this cartoon is just to show
that there are two components in this
flow but the essence is that the flow of
any system should exist has to do a hill
climbing on this log of probability so
now let's go back and put the Markov
blanket back into the mix and let's do
it in terms of the states that
constitute me my sensory states my
African states and my internal States
now that
til climbing behavior is still true
which means that it's still the case and
all my internal states will try to
maximize a log
Golic probability and all my actions or
my behaviors my acted states will also
try to maximize this quantity here I'm
going to associate these with perception
and actions and motivate that for you in
the rest of the talk but just to pause
for a moment and just think about what
this quantity means depending upon where
you were educated or what community you
come from what we're saying is that the
system will appear to self-organize
internally and behave in a way that it's
going to maximize this quantity which is
just the energy of states it thinks it
should be in it likes to occupy it's
just the variable states the adaptive
States from this we can then derive what
needs from a conceptual bridge to things
like reinforcement learning optical
control theory expected utility theory
and the like the negative value is just
the self informational surprisal or
surprise so any system that exists will
be trying to an information theoretic
sentence trying to minimize its surprise
and then that brings us to the principle
of maximum mutual information minimum
redundancy and the free energy principle
where free energy here provides a
wrapper variational bound or
approximation to the surprise itself the
time integral our path integral over any
trajectory will because of the ergodic
assumption is the entropy and that's
nice because the what this means is
there's a resistance to the second law
its resisting an increase in entropy and
of course that is the holy grail of self
in organizations energetic because it's
just a statement of homeostasis it's
just saying that systems biological
systems that reduce the tendency to
disorder keep themselves within
physiological balance and within very
nice examples of balance
terms of say the constraints on there's
loss functions or cost functions now as
a statistician you will also notice that
this quantity or e to the surprise is
the probability of sensory data given me
we find preparing me as a model of my me
and my environment then this is also
known as model evidence it's the
probability of the sensory samples
conditioned upon me existing or the
model existing which means that this can
be interpreted this maximization of this
quantity here can be interpret in terms
of the Bayesian brain evidence
accumulation and predictive coding and
that's these two perspectives about what
I want to pursue and try and unpack in
terms or process theories of how the
brain might work and how it might act so
just to give you a very quick flavor of
how the nature of the dynamics are dis
described what I've done here is if
simulate a little primordial soup using
a hundred and twenty eight
macromolecules that I've given
autonomous dynamics using a Lorenz
attractor so they each one has a has its
own dynamics of electrochemical sort and
their spatial relationships determing
forces amongst the molecules with weak
electrochemical attraction and strong
repulsion as a inverse function of their
euclidean separation and just lumping
these little macromolecules together
they sort of bubble away quite happily
showing obtain non equilibrium so they
stay quite quickly the details of the
simulation of completely unimportant you
get exactly the same behavior whatever
you whatever certain loosely coupled in
amical system you put you write down you
put a little bit of random fluctuations
in it will show this sort of behavior in
one parameter regime the reason I've
done that is because I've written down
the equations of motion and I now know
the physical separation and these
statistical coupling between these
molecules I now know that
structure that adjacency matrix which
means in principle I can go in there and
find some internal states and their
Markov blanket and I can then look at
that system and then do experimental way
to try to illustrate the two behaviors
that I was referring to before so we're
down here is it Ripley's exactly the
movie that we had on the previous slide
but here I've color-coded the internal
states in blue here and it'll ring here
with a small tail the active states in
red that surround the until state
support the sensory states or the
surface states that are exposed to the
external states in Siam yeah and this
thing is riddles around flapping its its
tail quite happily exchanging again in
non-equilibrium steady state with the
environment for those of you interested
it's very easy to find these these
structures you just need to identify the
mark of banking making for sure
constitutes I was constituted by the
parents the children the parents of the
children and then split it into the
active and sensitive States using the
look that the rules are described before
so what I'm now got is a sympathetic
little organism that I can now ask does
actually maintain the structural
function integrity of this often
referred to in terms of things like
order polices and do the internal states
imperfect act as little Bayesian engines
or infer the hidden causes of their
sensory states namely active inference
so just briefly to illustrate the sorts
of things which we do as neuroscientist
which we're basically performing brain
lesions or studying people with strokes
this is an illustration what happens
when you perturb the system so here are
the locations of those all the elements
of that little organism here reported in
terms of their locations over 512
seconds under normal progression and
these three panels show the equivalent
locations where I made my lesions to
either the active States
these are very modern I'm just rendering
them insensitive to the electrochemical
interactions coupling so this would be
like paralyzing the agent the sensory
states by making it blind or giving it a
little stroke by leading the internal
states and the key thing the obvious
thing here is that whatever I do I
basically kill the organism I destroy
its equilibrium and indeed we can assume
now that the you know the proper
maintenance of its structure and
function did depend upon that
hill-climbing behavior that I've
Illustrated in the first few slides
technically this is actually known as
oscillator death and it's closely
related to something else general a
synchronization which I'll I'll mention
in a second is the second illustration
here just for illustrative purposes all
to make a heuristic point anyway
I'm asking the question
is there anything in or don't do the
electrochemical states of the internal
states predict the physical motion of
the outside world so this would be like
a brain imaging experiment where I
present some moving stimuli in the
outside world I look for event responses
in the visual cortex of the brain and
it's very easy to find mixtures here
that if all the internal space lagged
over time by linear mixtures that do
indeed predict the motion of external
states here the degree of prediction and
color coded by the the this the depth of
this I am coloring here's the most
predictable motion of the most
predictable external molecule in shown
in the dotted line and the prediction is
a solid line and what's happening
occasionally this there this little
molecule here gets expelled
on the sweep and then falls back again
and it seems as if this thing is
actually predicting or registering these
external events despite the fact that
they are statistically conditionally
independent they're separated by the
Markov blanket
there is none Sheamus examples you can
almost see the fluctuation internal
states the Evoque response associated
with this outside motion event here if
you look carefully you can see that the
changes in the internal States actually
precede the external states which begs
an important question are the internal
states causing the external states or is
the external fluctuation causing and
registering a representation of a
statistical sort in the internal state
and of course the answer is both all
we're seeing here is an illustration of
generalized synchrony so I'm sure you
all know this but this is the phenomena
where if you originally observed by
Huygens where you have multiple clocks
hanging from the same wall or beam and
ultimately they have to come to swing in
synchrony there is that is their only
long-term attracting state this is one
of his drawings a to illustrate two
plots since when in fact the same beam
and that's all we're seeing it was
seeing a generalized synchrony between
internal and external States just by the
very existence of these random dynamic
attractors and here we can think about
one o'clock have air comprising the
internal states the other clock the
external states and their Markov blanket
the beam on the wall from which they are
suspended I like this example because it
highlights a complete symmetry of what's
going on here so if you subscribe to
this idea that we are trying to predict
and model our world what this means is
that the world is trying to model you in
an exactly symmetrical way the world is
watching you in exactly the same way
that you are watching the world so
that's all we sort of heavy lifting done
from the point of view of the
self-organization to summarize and the
existence of a Markov blanket
necessarily implies a partition of
states into internal States a Markov
blanket name is central active States an
external or hidden state and because
active States change but not
change by external states they minimize
the entropy of internal states in the
Markov blanket which means that action
will appear to maintain the structural
and functional integrity of a Markov
blanket and sent our internal states
will appear to infer the hidden causes
of sensory states by maximizing Bayesian
model evidence and influence those
hidden causes through action and we will
refer to that as an active imprint so
now what I want to do is just repeat the
exactly the same story but using a
different metric and the sorts of ideas
and perspectives that you'd find in
psychology and neuroscience but we're
going to be appealing to exactly the
same ideas the only slight difference
here is previously I had written down a
simulation where the value functional
cost functional at a surprise function
was an emergent property of the
differential equations here are actually
going to write down the the Gothic
density in terms of prior beliefs about
the about the the states that agents
like to occupy but the the actual
simulations and solutions that I'm going
to show you are basically exactly the
same a differential equation hill
climbing equation and if that the same
code so where this sort of talk normally
starts is with the Helmholtz so now
we're talking about the brain and the
brain as a constructive an organism that
constructs predictions and explanations
for its sensory inputs beautifully
articulated in terms in by this quote a
objects are always imagined as being
present in the field of vision as would
have to be there in order to produce the
same impression on the nervous system so
the brain is providing as its spending
predictions of our explanations or
hypotheses for the sensory input and is
updating or revising its internal
hypotheses in order to account for the
sensory evidence at
and this of course is very closely
related to the notion of perceptions
hypothesis testing by Richard Gregory
and has been formalized and articulated
by people like Peter Dan and Geoffrey
Hinton from a Bayesian perspective
borrowing from variational principles in
particular variational free-energy
invented by richard fineman
to solve the firm his particular quantum
electrodynamic old problems using
patented or approximations to the path
integral problems so that's what we're
going to this is a perspective we're
going to pursue this quote is nice that
in the sense that it induces its notion
of a sensory impression on the nervous
system which of course is very much like
the sense from States being or
reflecting external influences of the
external States are impressing
themselves on the the Markov blanket or
this veil to produce the sensory
impressions and if it is the case that
the internal states are maximizing the
MOT Bayesian model evidence they are
implicitly inferring the causes in the
outside world that produce that so let's
see what that might look like how that
might be implemented in a simple brain
like organism so here's our basic
hill-climbing equation again in its
Helmholtz form and replacing the
surprise with the free energy bound here
so we've actually a great descent on the
free energy here with its divergence
free and curl three components so nidal
components and just rewriting this
equation in a form that might be more
familiar to many of you it's basically a
Kalman filter so the the solenoidal
component now becomes a prediction in
the sense that prediction can't change
the model evidence because there's no
new data so it doesn't change the low
probabilities flows on the iso contours
whereas the update does the hill
climbing and that's just a minimization
of the dictionary way
by the precision of the prediction error
multiplied by the precision of the
random fluctuations so what's the
dictionary we've heard about that a
number of times it's basically the
difference between observations and some
some reference here let's assume that we
have these sensory impressions and that
we were trying to predict the cause of
these sensory impressions given some
expectation mu here and if I have a
generative model of forward model given
these expectations of what the sensory
consequences of these expected causes
were I can then produce a prediction in
sensory data space of sense of space
look at the difference and we'll call
that the prediction error and then all
we're saying is that if a system exists
then you should be able to write it down
so it looks as if it is always trying to
minimize its prediction error both by
changing its internal states which now
stand in for expectations of the causes
and through its action noticeable
there's no imperative here to actually
model the true external space it is just
a statement that it is sufficient to
understand the dynamics in terms of
minimization of prediction error so the
actual cause can be very different from
the true cause so that is good in the
sense that we've boiled down all the
behavior to a suppression of prediction
error and that provides a simple
intuitive
perspective on perception action in the
sense we can either change our brains to
make our predictions more like the
sensations or we can actually change the
way that were sampling the sensations to
make them more like the predictions both
in the service of minimizing prediction
error and this provides that like the
metaphor fracture and perception that I
was talking about previously but if this
rests upon prediction errors and clearly
I have to have
a model that generates predictions at
this point would we start to get into
some of the hard problems now so let's
just think about the nature of the Jered
models that would actually generate data
that a humanoid robot or a human
actually samples from the world and
let's say you set your students the task
of generating foveal sampling from a
synthetic retina now to do that just to
generate the data let's not worry about
inferring or inverting any model just to
generate the data you're going to have
to know the hidden causes the what and
the where of what of the causes of these
sensory data so you need to know what
was what is the object being visually
palpated what is where are we looking
what are the kinetics of that saccadic
search and then we'd mix these two
causes with a cascade of non linear
convolution operators londonium mappings
different hierarchical levels to finally
produce the actual sampled data I've
just written down that deep and dynamic
Garrett of a forward model here in terms
of hidden states or causes and hidden
States per se all subject to random
fluctuations eventually generating
sensory consequences right at the bottom
and now if we apply our hill-climbing
function clueless and then rewrite the
message passing implicit in this
gradient descent here using the some of
the Kalman filter based formulation of
this we have to get a very very similar
architecture we replace the random
fluctuations with prediction errors but
the expectations which now replace the
hidden states have exactly the same form
they're just cascading down generating
predictions of the expectations at lower
levels right down to the bottom level
now the interesting thing here from the
point of view of a
neuroanatomist is that we actually
create forward or ascending connections
or message-passing
where the prediction errors are
propagated up or deep into the hierarchy
to update or correct our expectations so
there's a reciprocal message passing
with descending predictions and a
counter stream or ascending prediction
errors all being mixed together in a
relatively simple way although there are
non the outers in this because the
predictions of in the pitching errors
are generated by nonlinear descending
influences here but a fast simple and
efficient way basically to map from
consequences and consequences back to
causes in a way that's consistent with
maximizing Bayesian model evidence so
just intuitively from the point of view
of again say a visual neuroscientist
let's to see how that might pan out in
terms of anatomy and physiology we have
sensory input coming in here
there are top-down predictions from the
visual cortex they are compared to
elaborate of addiction error that the
declare is passed up to the visual
hierarchy to revise expectations about
the causes of that say local pattern of
sensory input but these predictions or
expectations themselves are in receipt
of higher predictions which form a
second-level prediction error that can
be sent up the hierarchy to revise
higher and higher more abstract
hierarchical deep representations and
we've heard about the importance of sort
of dimension reduction of factorization
and in the formation or in the use of
these hierarchical models that are
defined by the factorization their
sparse tree structure this is where you
get the dimension reduction the
efficient representation explanation for
sensory important we can tell exactly
the same story for proprioceptive input
so perceptive input from stretch
receptors here in the Oakland A's system
coming to the pontine nuclei in the
suite of top-down predictions say from
the frontal eye fields
we have a prediction er that could be
sent forward to revise our beliefs about
the configuration of our oculomotor
system and provide a Bayes optimal
explanation for that but and here's the
important thing
these prediction errors have another way
of suppressing themselves they can
coupled directly back to the actuators
to make the stretch correspond to the
descending proprioceptive prediction so
they can eliminate themselves quickly
and efficiently just by coupling back to
the environment so this is the action
this is basically action minimizing
prediction error here notice that the
only thing that action can change are
the prediction errors of the first level
not deep in the hierarchy and what I've
described there is simply a reflex are
nothing more nothing less in this
perspective basically the descending
predictions provide the reference for
the reflexes to fulfill so action is in
the game again changing the sampled
sensations to make them more like the
predictions including the predictions
about the motor plant not only in the
synthesis about the motor plant as I
really have the reflexes right at the
bottom of the of the hierarchy so these
predictions of course are not simple
they are richly informed by deep
hierarchical processing and gathering
together of all information from all
modalities so these are descending
predictions that are just in the
proprioceptive domain but they all
internally consistent with beliefs about
the world and its history that have been
appeared that have benefitted from the
accumulation of multimodal information
so these are very rich descending
predictions but their actual realization
by the motor plant is trivial it's just
driven by the reflex arc here so these
will be basically the retina reference
signals
we were hearing about it earlier on so
person is that before I conclude with a
couple of illustrations biological
agents minimize their average surprising
that their entropy they do this by
suppressing but you can write this down
in terms of the suppression of the
dictionary and that can be reduced by
either changing the predictions named
with deception or sensations to action
and this certainly speed the predictive
processing of Kalman filtering scheme
that I just described entailed return
message passing to optimize predictions
and action with flexibly makes those
predictions come true and thereby
minimizes surprise so I mean it's now
conclude by giving you a working through
three examples and sort of build upon
each other which may be and speak more
to robotics and open up time yeah so
wait a minute I was just about to
accelerate there into hyperdrive now
more relaxed ago though big deal is to
partner up never loop time for
discussion
so the first at the first so I was
trying to think how all the ideas I've
been I've been hearing about this
morning fit with this scheme and there
are lots of points of contact but there
are also points of confusion for me so
I'm hoping that some that will be
resolved by by the audience and often
that my confusion is resolved by going
back to these simple toy examples
yourself evidently work so the first
example it was basically how would you
simulate cued region so there's some
change in the environment accuse a
particular movement and that movement is
just wreaking to target so this is
actually a trivial thing to solve from
the point of view of this active infant
scheme and just involves putting into
the model that prior beliefs that when a
target changes color there is an
invisible spring or an invisible
spinning that is
connected from the target to the tip of
the agents finger becomes very stiff
from poles of the finger to the target
so in the absence of any cue change that
string has no stiffness but as soon as
the target changes the agent believes
that there is an attractive force
pulling its finger towards the target
now if it believes that then and that is
part of its generative model then it
would expect to see and feel its arm
move to the target and action will
reflexively
fulfill that and in so doing will also
fulfill the visual predictions this is
basically the sort of behavior we get
when the target changes from green to
red this is just a schematic of the
implementation by reflexes through
action of these descending
proprioceptive predictions here so I
think the interesting point here is that
the forward model that implicitly
resolves the you know multiple degrees
of freedom problem is very simple and
it's got absolutely nothing to do with
the real world the real world does not
contain Springs the actual model is
almost a heuristic and heuristic used in
a very good sense so I think that
heuristics then sometimes come along
with a slightly negative connotation but
in fact heuristics are your priors and a
profit Bayesian inference they are at
the heart of everything and as you know
at the very end of the final
presentation we have this sort of
hierarchical decomposition almost you
know appealing to he respects at the
very high level constructs this I think
form is exactly the same as a heart a
deep hierarchical genitive model where
the priors induce the call empirical
processes in a hierarchical model like
there are heuristics then are the right
nor wrong and of course once you get the
action of making them come true there
they come right provided they are
allowed
so if you've got the right heuristics
they are true they're just privates and
in this instance these prior beliefs
resolve the usual in motor control
problem because you're actually pulling
not pushing you don't have to solve an
approaching problem you're solving a
pulling problem by use of this
particular and very simple try of
heuristic or pry belief that's just part
of it a very simple part of the
differential equation that constantly
with the hierarchical generative model
so this example essentially uses a point
attractor so the equations of motion
that describe this pry belief or this
heuristic have a fixed attracting point
the next example just takes exactly the
same idea but with two twists first of
all we're going to make the target
invisible and now it's not going to have
a point attractor the location of this
effective target is now going to pursue
a head returning cycle and we've heard
about central pattern generators I'm
just writing down that a central pattern
generator actually has a Volterra lock
to form that produces a heavy clinic
cycle that attracts the effective
location of this point in Euclidean
though at extra personal space to a
series of unstable fixed points and
again it it's likely that the notion of
computing your points of contact and
then working out the dynamics has a lot
of similarity in the way that one chance
and sequences but what we're doing here
with so this one equation set a very
simple equation
I repeat a local terror differential
equation that has a number of unstable
fixed points that are visited in
sequence this is just nothing more or
less than a central pattern generator
and then there's a mapping from the
location in this abstract space to
certain points in the 2d planar space
that attracted the finger in exactly the
same way with the point attractor
attracted the finger before and by
different putting these points here in
an appropriate place I can simulate the
writing that you've just guess
being traced out there now so there's an
interesting simulation from the
biologist's point of view because the
activity of the units that are encoding
these privates and generation
predictions that have been filled by
action do actually show a lot of
characteristics that people in
neurosciences familiar with so for
example if I plot the activity of one of
these in terms of the position in space
we get placed cell activity furthermore
we get placed in activity that has
Direction selectivity prefers the
downstroke as personally as both of the
J here and another nice thing about this
simulation it actually shows that or it
allows me to remind myself and remind
you all this behavior has been produced
by deep dynamic descending predictions
in the proprioceptive domain at the same
time the agent is making visual
predictions and feeling the consequences
of its behavior and it's well happy
because those predictions are completely
fulfilled however if I just reduced the
gain on these descending predictions I
now have a Sun replay the same visual
input I now have a simulation scenario
where it will be like the agent watching
somebody else right and yet it can use
exactly the same forward model to infer
the trajectory and what is being written
and I simulated that here in terms of
looking at the activity of this unit
here when I've precluded in the movement
by switching up the gain of these
descending illusions but left these in
play and then exam replayed the visual
input to the agent and it excites
exactly the same selective responses in
the same forward model so it's using
this generative model that has multi
modal X receptive and proprioceptive
predictions in the one hand to prescribe
behavior through descending
proprioceptive predictions but also in
other context it can prescribe the X
receptacle visual contour all the
consequences of another's behavior so it
can also accumulate sensory evidence to
infer what something else
what another
but was doing the course that's
basically the premise of the mirror
neuron system which this provides a very
crude model okay finally what we did
there was write down explicitly the
number of the attracting locations what
I want to do now is to show you the last
the last simulation that asked the
question well how do we in visual
neuroscience identify the points of
attraction the next point of attraction
in this electrically itinerant sampling
of our sensory space and the way that
I'm going to choose those is this is the
second equation here when you choose
those is actually quite principled it I
won't go into the arguments now but
basically rests upon the following
argument that if it is the case that all
systems that exist in allegoric sense
can be written down in terms of
minimizing their variational free energy
and if it is the case that the behavior
of all systems is determined by the
empirical prize or the priors inherent
in the model that forms the basis of
that free energy their heuristics what
are the only necessary heuristics to
explain the existence of a system that
doesn't go through them off expression
Airi to plus or minus infinity well it's
just that they believe that they
minimize the energy so if that system
believes it minimizes free energy in the
future then it will act to fulfill that
belief and it will therefore minimize
free energy and it will therefore exist
so what does that mean in terms of
understanding the imperatives for
planned action or if you like goal
directed actual and I haven't got a I
won't go into this it is a very
interesting sort of game if one writes
out the full expression for expected
free engine in the future it actually
entails a lot of interesting things that
subsume optimal control and K
control but I'm actually taking the sort
of the the interesting bits out of the
lost function that make its or loss
functions that you would deal with and
just leave them looking at what is left
what is actually left is the information
gain or the epistemic value the
reduction in certainty I would get if I
move like this
so as applied to the visual domain that
simply means that we're going to the
point of tractors of our eyes or ocular
motor system are going to be those
movements that harvest or solicit or
elicit sensory samples that reduce my
uncertainty about the state of the world
and we can compute that so if I have
this hypothesis about that this image
was causing my local sensory sample so
you haven't moved this circle around
compute the decrease in expected free
energy conditioned upon that control and
score it in terms of information gain
epistemic value and create a salience
map I can now use the Maxima of those
sailors maps to drive that itinerant
searching exactly the realist rate in
the previous slide here's the
architecture I will go into this it's
not very interesting more interesting
thing here is the behavior so here the
locations of this successive or tunnel
autonomously selected now at acting
points for successive successive
fixations in a movie format these are
the data bit of sample stimulated EOG s
or electrical I move of recordings the
visual samples at the end of each is a
card and this is the interesting thing
in this simulation this very simple
agent have beliefs that the world could
either be an upside down plays a
sideways face or a vertical face and it
then sampled information to resolve its
uncertainty or confusion about what the
state of the world was that was causing
its sensory information that's now shown
here in terms of the expectations for
the correct explanation which was the
upright face
the incorrect explanations and the 97
days and confidence intervals just to
show that there is a within Sicard
between saltatory between Sicard
reduction and transit inflation of
uncertainty as this agent goes and
gathers bits of information then
progresses really resolves its
uncertainty about what's going on beyond
its Markoff blanket and clearly if any
evidence violated or disconfirm desai
policy would then move to the next
competing hypothesis very much in like a
windowless as one would in a windless
competition or I'm gonna take all like
situation so I'll conclude with that
example it would have been nice to
further example that spoke more directly
to robotics but I do help on I'm sorry
nor is that our expertise but I will
close with a quote from Helmholtz that I
think again wonderfully summarizes
everything that I've just said a
movement we make by which we alter the
appearance of objects would be thought
of as an experiment designed to test
whether we would have understood
correctly the in variations of the
phenomena before us that is the existent
the existence in definite spatial
relations and with that I'd like to
thank all the people whose ideas I've
been talking about and of course thank
you for your attention thank you very
much indeed
and I have a question that relates to
your pointing example that you then
extend it
I think it's too
this didn't do not really well
Misaka we must address for a fixed part
Photography
interesting
plus the sequences
with the exception think about
I'm just coming experience
the states
it's ours
it's fun
a whole sweater
yeah
oh I think community people who could
come and lecture on the importance of
variational free energy and approximant
Bayesian inference that is exactly to
finesse that problem so if I understand
your problem the problem you're you're
highlighting if it were the case that
one could actually evaluate P of s if
you could actually estimate surprise or
value then in principle you could just
work out the gradients with respect to
control variables and with respect to
internal states and and then is write
down the differential equation something
you know a very adaptive agent that
could be and while it would add that
everything every aspect including the
parameters would have to minimize for
energy and if you write that down that
becomes associative learning Instamatic
time it then becomes an atlas sectional
bayesian model selection and
evolutionary time but everything
minimizes that log energy that locket
surprised because you can't measure it
and as I understand it this is exactly
the problem problem the mission pieman
confronted when he was trying to solve
the pathetical problem to work out the
probability of trajectories of small
particles of little united state funds
and it can't be analytically solve and
it certainly can't be don't possibly
every evolutionary time with some you
know and see at something technique but
in real time that times of hence the
free energy so the free energy provides
an analytic bound that is really easy to
measure but it renders now your optimal
dynamic no longer is it a percept phase
in infants it now becomes known as
approximate phase in infants so the
whole point of the free energy principle
as opposed to just maximizing bethe
model evidence or maximizing minimizing
surprise is that it'll I was exactly
Paul that it provides a tractable
finessing of the problem that you're
talking about so everything I've talked
about is an approximate Bayesian
inference which lends another aspect I
guess to the use of the word
so the free energy which is always by
definition by it gives inequality bigger
than the the thing that we'd like to
measure to the log of the probability
itself now can be written down this form
so and then it has a flavor and I feel
where sudden you feel comfortable
because you you know and talk about
likelihood models we know and talk about
prize if you're comfortable with
hierarchical models or deep models you
will also be comfortable the notion of
parametric empirical Bayes and empirical
prize so these are the things that you
are forced to do when doing modeling
because we cannot measure usually for
nonlinear models the actual thing we
want to approximate which is the
probability of s so probability of s
given M does not appear in this equation
but what we now have to do is to write
down the prize the like it explicitly
and notice that the entropy term is on
the end here so this conforms to James's
maximum entropy principle so we're
trying to maximize basically the
accuracy of our model whilst at the same
time maximizing the entropy or the
uncertainty in our explanation it's very
paradoxical but this is what leads to
the generalization and the simply the
simplicity this is packaging of the
apartment bayesian solutions and again
I'm thinking about your presentations
you know that was part of that that
that's a simplexity of procures and the
opponent abuse of the word that the the
minimization of the complexity that you
would you get from including this
entropy term tells you or usually makes
it the case that past models with nice
fast hierarchical structures with low
dimensions as of its
explanations for high dimensional data
have much more evidence or more exactly
lower free energy than models that don't
have that low dimensionality so you can
actually write this equation out in
number different ways and and that
complexity becomes a kr divergence
between the post view in the prior
and that the determinant of that
complexity which is all part of this
completely standard free energy national
free energy variation or bayes ensemble
learning and performing ISM you get for
free when you use low dimensional
hierarchical models of you later so I
think there's a principle drive to
getting to those good heuristics I have
the low dimensionality with that
hierarchical temporal structuring we've
been talking about it's actually
mandated by the very nature of the
problem that we're trying to solve or
trying to explain ok so this
relationship between Bayesian inference
and an optimal control that that you get
out of course it's the old idea going
back to cowman and in his world in the
in the linear world there 1 to n just
like you described but later the word
world by meter and flaming in the
nonlinear case and then I did something
and work up and did something relating
into path integrals and collectively we
figured out that control is actually a
much bigger problem than Bayesian
inference specifically what that means
is that there is a subclass of
stochastic optimal control problems that
map want to 1/2 Bayesian inference
involving the same dynamical system but
there are infinitely many other
stochastic optimal control problems that
do not have a inference analog and the
reason is very simple actually if you
look at base true and the fokker-planck
and the Kushner equation they're all
linear the hamilton-jacobi bellman
equation is nonlinear there is a special
case where it becomes linear under of
logarithmic transformation but it's not
always the case so I'm wondering you
must have made an assumption somewhere
along the way that proved a very large
class of control problems and I didn't
follow also where the presented I'm
guessing you started by saying that P
dot is 0 you kind of assume some kind of
statistical equilibrium in the world
which doesn't have to be true to great
questions but not the very last few
words when a couple of different
questions and
no question I've got a lot of stuff for
example a lot of the things that I
showed they cannot be right I can but I
was cute another pet one look at the P
dot 0 is is more just a statement on the
conditions that we need to comply with
so I was careful to say non-equilibrium
steady-state so we're not talking about
equilibrium we're we're talking about
systems that move and change and
fluctuate so by definition so if I
wanted to talk about systems that have
attracting sets that have measurable
characteristics over extended periods of
time
basically the gentec-eo dissolved so
that that assumption was ready to
motivate the variational formulation of
the hill climbing on surprise that was
not a programmatic constraint on the on
the solutions that I used to illustrate
the ideas it's really a more fundamental
motivation for where you get that
fundamental hill climbing from in the
first place but it doesn't it does not
entail stationarity it does not entail
in either a wide sensor or a weak sense
it is not incident Intel thermodynamics
or any other form of equilibrium it's
steady state in the sense that P dot 0
Pease dot is equal to 0 I think the the
BB or the more interesting question
I don't know I what clearly I haven't
gone through the the formalism that
would map specifying the problem in
terms of loss functions and how that
translates into baden inference
however the simple answer to that is
that all the lost functions that are
implicit in the illustrations here and
elsewhere are all written down as log
Prize so as long as we can write down
your loss function in terms of a prior
preference or a prior energy in the log
of the prior belief then by definition
it
a Bayesian inference problem so the
question I think then for all nonlinear
and dynamical models so that's one of
the conditions for doing this setting up
these dualities that the any energy cost
has to be a Kerr divergence between some
passive and some active dynamic but
there is another important requirement
which is that any noise that comes into
the system must live in your control
space in other words if anything
happened by accident you should have
been able to do it yourself and that's
the thing that's actually a very strong
assumption so for example if I'm a robot
I'm kind of shaking due to noise but my
mother could have made me shake in the
same way we can test that is based in
infants but if somebody came and pushed
me you know that I couldn't have pushed
myself all of a sudden that's not a
Bayesian inference problem it has to do
with the noise the structure of the
noise and not just with that I mean I'm
gonna have to defer to you technically
you know more I have been doing this I
would say that this pushing you know in
the sense when we get new visual
information we are being pushed
informational e via sensory and of
course the whole point of bit Kalman
filtering and you know the
generalizations of that of course this
is not Kalman filtering this is this is
beyond extended Kalman filtering the
factors in generalized coordinates
emotions and generalized Bayesian
filtering but that putting is of course
just from the sensory perspective
exactly the problem that generalized
Bayesian filtering content with and
result and let me prints the question
back to you how is pushing the retina
with visual information any different
from putting my proprioception buying
you know a force to my body
my question is a bit naive but if I
understood well that your internal state
is like the brain the state of the brain
and the the external state in the
outside world of the brain right but the
dynamics involved all state so the
attractor for example contains also the
the external state the internal state in
the so while the internal strengths are
actually just model in the external
space not themselves there again the
internal States are understood as
modeling the external States but not
themselves I've kind of feel that the
dynamic model was including all states
and that the the dynamic was including
Nekomata general with all states right
all slaves in the outside world but not
the states that are doing the modeling
well does it matter your question
because because I didn't see exactly in
the equation that you had well why the
the Markov blanket was playing in the
market demarco Markov blanket assumption
what are we coming into the equation I
see so the leap there again I apologize
for rushing over that that's actually
very non-trivial it's basically this
thing here isn't it yeah I think
everybody would be whoops would be
fairly comfortable they would after half
an hour the MATLAB or a pen and paper
they'd be fairly comfortable with this
and it's really why is this still true
this basically looks as if it has
eliminated the external state remember
as far as the sensory active and
internal states but not the external
states and yet the this lot probability
depends upon the experience a so that's
the clever bit that's the non-trivial
aspect of this result so this result
still holds true when you have to go
through and actually do the integration
to cure it in a non trivial way so this
has the same form as the previous
equation oops my point
so FX is a curly greater descent on this
thing here where X comprises everything
this is also true but this probability
distribution here depends upon the
external states so that's the clever bit
in the sense that it's as if the
internal states and the active state or
more the owner of it it's as if the
internal states somehow know about the
external space they know where they are
in the states based on external States
and yet they can't because that's beyond
the Markov blanket but the very
existence of non-equilibrium steady
state means that this has to be true and
that's basically what gives these well
what if what it is what gives these
systems or certainly a focus on the
internal set of an over system and the
Markov blanket the look and feel of
adapted behavior the look and feel of
self-organization homeostasis and the
look and feel of a little Bayesian agent
thank you very much again and my
question is more naivety and how the
biological neural network is
implementing well I think that's an open
question and as open as the best theme
that one would you know adopt in the
robotics context so what you're asking
is what what is the the the process
theory that complies with the with with
the principle I mean the principle in of
itself is almost uninteresting because
it's tautologically true I think the
hard problem is really first of all the
form of the genitive models that you're
dealing with and the actual scheme that
is used to do the liberation the energy
minimization which could be selection
using basic model selection it could be
it could be and I concur with the
enthusiasm for gauss-newton schemes
certainly all our simulations
essentially use a Gauss Newton scheme
why well because under the particular
form of approximate Bayesian inference
which is not exact given by assuming the
posterior is always Gaussian you can
always write it down as a in terms of
minimizing petitioner when you can do
that you can move from it you can move
from a Newton to a Gaussian scheme with
all the computational savings involved
so you don't have to explicitly evaluate
the curvature or the Hessian so and that
rests upon the fact that you've made
this for class assumption in the in
defining the variable free energy so
that's part of the approximation here
masses of computational saving all sorts
of one of the things
just drop out for free under that
Laplace assumption so we like we in
terms of neuroscientists and people with
very small computers using MATLAB like
the like the predictive coding
formulation or Kalman filtering applying
a Kalman gain to a perpendicular and
that is very understandable in terms
again I haven't gotten the right
graphics here but it's very
understandable in terms of the sorts of
message passing you see in the real
brain so these actually usually thought
to be equivalent superficial pyramidal
cells that live about a millimeter from
the cortical surface the expectations
are thought to be encoded by D pyramidal
cells which live about four millimeters
in the deeper layers of the cortex
visual cortex is exactly this
hierarchical structure it has exactly
the right sort of a Hammond of
specificity layer specificity deep and
superficial it also has the right
functional asymmetries remember before I
said there are non the outages in this
but these are in the generation of a
prediction error through the nonlinear
forward model which means that these
descending predictions are nonlinear
whereas these are linear and driving as
in the Kalman filter so these particular
formulations will normally be with
normally associate continuous-time
representations of the post
we get into sitting in society
basic belief obtained or belief
propagation the lack of a formal
distinction is between predictive coding
and generalized Bayesian filtering
schemes that deal with continuous state
and continuous time whereas most of the
microscopic models actually look at this
in the neural chemistry of personality
responses they only work the state space
model this discrete states you know you
in state Wallen k with very very large
vectors so there's a formal distinction
then then you're outside the game
they'll have been using protein
predictive coding so you've got you've
got your choice so if they do more
question go to lunch now and we want to
thank the speaker again back in the room
at 1:45